Okay, good evening everyone. Thank you
very much for coming. I'm Chris from the
Padantic team and uh yeah, we're
delighted that you've you've come along
tonight. Uh this was a very
oversubscribed event, so apologies to
any colleagues of yours who weren't able
to make it tonight. We're videoing this
uh and we're going to send it out to
people who couldn't make it tonight. So,
um you can let them know that if they
couldn't come along. We've got a really
exciting series of four lightning talks
tonight. I'm going to introduce each one
as they come along, but uh they're going
to be excellent. Um, important stuff to
know is that uh there'll be a brief Q&A
after each talk. Each talk will be about
15 minutes long. Um, but we're going to
keep the Q&A to like two three
questions. So, so pretty brief. Um,
we're really thankful to Atomico for
letting us host the event here in this
great space as you can see. Um, so
before we begin the talks, I'm just
going to hand over to Mara from Atomico
to give us a few words from Atomico.
Thank you and so great to see everyone
tonight. Uh welcome to Atomico HQ. Just
wanted to say a few brief words on
actually who we are in case that might
be interesting for some of you. So
Atomico, we're one of the largest and
oldest panuropean VC funds. We've been
around since 2006 and started by
Nicholas Denstrom, the founder and CEO
of Skype, who's still our CEO and at the
helm of the firm. Um we invest across
multiple stages. So from seeds to preipo
with a check size between two and $50
million. Um and have a platform team
that supports our portfolio companies in
any stage of growth. So in case you're a
founder or maybe thinking of becoming
one, uh feel free to ping me or find me
later. I'm Marta atomico.com. Uh very
nice to have you all. Uh and enjoy the
evening. Back to you. Great. Thank you.
Okay. I'm very pleased to introduce
Jason Louu. Jason is a machine learning
engineer, independent consultant, and
angel investor. And after working at top
tech companies, he now teaches
organizations to approach AI more
scientifically, focusing on measurement,
rapid iteration, and meaningful
outcomes. He created Instructor, a
Python library for structured outputs
from LLMs, and that's got over 1 million
monthly downloads, and that inspired
OpenAI's structured output feature. Uh
Jason has consulted for companies like
Zapia and HubSpot whilst also developing
educational content including his
popular rag course um which I can
personally attest is excellent. So
without further ado, over to you Jason.
There we are. Testing testing. All
right, cool. Uh yeah, thanks everyone
for coming. Uh let me just jump into
some slides. Basically, this is kind of
a condensed version of some of the stuff
that I teach a lot of different
companies. And in particular, my goal
today is really to help you think about
how to look at data using techniques
like clustering. And most importantly,
recognizing that a lot of the things
that you have to do to improve your AI
applications is not actually improving
the AI. Once you look at data, I'll give
a bunch of examples of how things really
improve and how things work in in the
real world. And a lot of times it's
about the inventory and the capabilities
of what you do versus the AI itself. And
ideally I can sort of share a little bit
about how logfire can help you measure
things and then you can eventually turn
them into tools and expose them to MCP
and we'll see if they can uh connect
together. So yeah um not everyone might
know me. My background is mostly
actually in like mathematical physics
and computational mathematics. Uh my
time at Meta was mostly spent doing
things like content analysis for cyber
crime. And so I I basically started
working on like rag applications to
figure out where like the worst things
on the internet were. That was in like
2016. Uh for the most of my career I
actually worked at a company called
StitchFix where I worked on things like
recommendation systems like
observability unironically and also
looking at things like generative AI for
images and and text to do better search
and I managed things like data curation
teams and a lot of search products. And
so when I started doing my own
consulting I kind of lucked out because
this thing called rag came out and I
basically felt like I was pretty
comfortable claiming you know five years
of experience doing uh rag. And since
then, I've worked on a bunch of
different companies. I created a library
called Instructor, well known for this
talk called a pyantic is all you need.
And if you see me on Twitter, I'm just
kind of spending some time over there.
And the reason I've been doing this is
actually because I had a hand injury in
2023, 2022, and so I really couldn't uh
code anymore. And so a lot of my time
now is just yapping, but I would rather
be coding as well. And uh yeah, a lot of
my time was spent figure how vision can
help us make money in 2017. and now it's
about how I can help you make money with
text. Um, and yeah, these are just some
of the companies I've worked with and
these are some of the companies I've
trained. Uh, it's been really fun to
basically try to be right and hopefully
save you guys time by uh sort of being
able to share a lot of what what I've
learned. And so the goal of this talk
really is to understand what does it
mean to systematically improve rack
applications.
I think most people think of rag as just
retrieval augmented generation but
really what happens is it's really just
a an LLM wrapping a recommendation
system and recommendation systems have
multiple retrieval tools right you know
we might have different tools to
understanding like inventory within
certain warehouses scoring different
functions understanding like margins of
pricing or something like that you know
filtering on preferences so ultimately a
real production application uh looks
like a recommendation system and this is
the general flywheel on how we think
about improving these things. Uh I'm not
going to jump over everything, so you're
welcome to take a picture, you know, DM
me on on uh Twitter later, but the
general idea is you want to think about
synthetic data, having very fast
evaluations, clustering, and I basically
being able to double down on the things
that matter and trying to say no to the
work that is really hard to figure out.
And you know, modern rag effectively is
just having a portfolio of tools, right?
It's not actually just doing a single
API call to search and then hoping the
AI works. you know deep research
effectively is a rag application
searches application you know and and I
think a lot of the most economically
valuable forms of genai like claude code
and cursor it's basically a rag
application right some of the really big
performance improvements cursor has made
is really actually using embeddings to
figure out like where your cursor should
jump into for the next tab
action and my goal today is to teach you
about how to look at your data so if you
come up with an example from marketing
right you can imagine you run a
marketing campaign and you find out that
80% % there was a 80% boost in sales or
an 80% downturn in sales, right? It's
never really just the case that you have
to make your marketing better in the
same way that you don't just be told
that you got to make the AI better,
right? What actually happens in
practice, you'll do some data analysis
and maybe you can come back and say,
"Hey, Jason, I think 60% of all the
increase in revenue came from the 30 to
45 year old women in the Midwest, right?
We should do something about that. Maybe
we can invest in that audience. Maybe we
can figure out where that audience comes
from. Maybe you learn that 10% of the
audience is reduc is producing like 60%
of the returns and maybe 40% of the
audience producing 10% of the returns.
If you have this information, you can do
a lot better with your marketing
campaign. And this is the same thing
when it comes to improving a
applications. A lot of it is
understanding what people are asking,
what they're asking for, and who's
asking. And once you figure out these
different segments, the expected value
or the ROI of your application is
effectively this very simple equation.
It's the impact times the number of
queries times the probability that the
query is successful. You can think of
that as maybe better citations, better
quality and generation. The relevancy is
going to matter. Maybe it's going to be
a proxy of how you measure success. And
what's going to happen is if you can do
any kind of offline analysis or online
analysis of these segments, whether it's
impact, the volume, or the success,
you're going to have a really easy time
understanding how to prioritize the
work, right? All right. And the real
challenge is going to be understanding
things like how do we do user research
to figure out what's useful? How do we
measure this probability of success? And
can we in some ways control this query
volume? If we have queries that we can't
do very well, we should probably do
something about that. If there are
things that are doing very well but low
volume, maybe we can do something about
that as well. And generally, if we can
have good user feedback, maybe it's a
thumbs up button or a thumbs down
button, again, we can figure out what is
the problem.
Like one simple thing that we've done at
Zapier, for example, is just changing
the copy as well, right? As long as
you're asking very specific questions on
what you want to measure, you're going
to get the thing you want. If you have
copy that says like, how did we do?
Maybe it's maybe it's slow, maybe the
lang language is incorrect, maybe it's
something else. It's going to be really
hard to understand what you're trying to
do. But if you ask the question, do we
answer your question? That's going to be
much more correlated with business
outcomes. And your goal is to measure
this across many segments. If you don't
have user feedback, you can also look at
things like maybe whether or not code is
being accepted. Maybe we're whether or
not we're sharing something or
publishing something. This is what like
perplexity does. And all of this helps
you collect that feedback. And then once
you can do the segmentation, you're
going to you're going to have two
different axes. You're going to have
user satisfaction on the bottom. And
then you're going to have query volume
at the top. High satisfaction, high
volume. That's basically just means that
you're kind of crushing it. If you do
high satisfaction, low volume, maybe
here you got to change something about
your UI, teach users how to build your
business or use your product, right? A
lot of the things here is just small UX
changes. Um, and you know, for example,
like if you want to have different
prompts to generate code, you can just
have a little button, click that, maybe
it prefills a prompt and now you're just
educating the user that these are
certain capabilities that matter. If
it's low satisfaction, low volume,
chances are you just want to say no,
right? Add a prompt that says, "Hey, we
can't do this. go call your manager and
this is going to save us a lot of pain
and obviously there's going to be
something that is going to be the lowest
performance system and that's basically
how you prioritize. This sounds very
obvious, but you'll be surprised at how
many companies don't do this or don't
understand what's important and what's
not important. Right? When I was working
with a bunch of companies, they would
spend time building out these
integrations and we just go back and say
like, have you ever checked how many
people use these integrations? And ends
up being, you know, 50% of your team is
allocated to a problem that only 10% of
your customers care
about. And when you identify these
segments, you're going to find two
different kinds of segments. Either the
AI is bad because there's a lack of
inventory or the AI is bad because
there's lack of capabilities. Right?
Inventory means that you don't have the
same data connectors or the same corpus.
And capabilities means that there's some
metadata that you don't have access to
or some metadata you can't filter
against. Right? How many times have I
asked a question that filters against
who created a document or when a
document was created or when was the
last time something changed. Now,
understanding that you got to ask these
questions changes how you might want to
index your data. Right? For example,
there's been companies where people ask
the question, "What has changed in this
document?" And you can't tell because we
overwrite the text chunks, right? This
is not an AI issue. This is just an
infrastructure issue. And again,
understanding all of this and having a
framework to think about this helps you
with this prioritization. It makes the
systematic part very systematic. And it
ultimately makes improving these systems
very boring because you have to figure
out what is the worst thing you're
you're doing. If you think of inventory
and different AI systems, you can think
of, you know, early Amazon. If you
search early Amazon and you go on like
batteries or televisions, you get
nothing because they only sell books.
And the solution here is expanding your
inventory, right? If you search like
Spanish tenobos on Netflix, again, it's
not the AI's fault. You just have to go
buy more shows or build more subtitles.
This is how you make search better. You
have better inventory. And the example
that is actually pretty real that my
friend told me about was uh Greek
restaurants near me. It turns out Door
Dash solved this problem by just buying
10,000 iPads and sending them to Greek
restaurants, right? None of this is the
AI. And you can figure this out by
looking at things like poor search
results, low cosign similarity. Maybe
the re-rankers are giving low scores.
These are all real issues. We've had
issues with data pipelines where we do
this analysis, we find a segment that
has data issues and it turns out the
connectors been broken for three months
or someone said this would be
implemented and it wasn't and this is a
way of detecting that. And these are the
things that you can use something like
Logar to
capture. And then we can get into
capability issues. Again, you go back to
Amazon affordable heels with less than
three inches of heels. Do we have the
metadata? Can we filter that? Is
affordable some absolute measure? Is it
a subjective measure where you have to
build a like client model? Again, these
are not really the AI's fault that you
can't filter this. A lot of it is going
to be how you index your data and how
you support data. Oscar nominated films,
right? does films that include the word
Oscar Isaac uh like are they relevant?
No. But it turns out Netflix just like
buys a CSV file from like IMDb and this
fixes everything, right? Again, if you
search like Chinese food after 9:00 p.m.
like you got to build out this like open
now button and have this filter on
what's available, what's not available.
And maybe some of these restaurants have
really bad availability times and
they're out of date. Turns out these are
all the problems that you got to solve
to make your AI really, really good, but
it's not really the language model's
fault. And so many times the companies I
work with have these issues and they're
mostly inventory or mostly capability
issues. Common capabilities at least for
these rag applications is having things
like daytime filters or being able to
compare multiple things. This just means
you got to search multiple indices,
right? Filtering against tabular data in
PDFs. Uh one example that was really
silly was we had a rag application
question over financial data and they
had no way of filtering all the
documents to a single stock ticker right
and just by doing that we improved
precision from like 50% to 90% and this
is like a really trivial implementation
right and now you can because you have
this plus comparisons and time filters
you can now compare the earnings calls
of Uber andyft and know that every
document is relevant rather than just
like hoping the embedding for the word
lift is mentioned.
Right? You know, even things like
understanding metadata for a lot of like
uh construction use cases, we found that
that people were asking questions like
who modified this file last or what has
changed so they can figure out who to
contact and most of the information was
actually about reading a document,
knowing who to call afterwards, right?
And that's inventory and capabilities.
That's basically looking at the modified
date, mapping that to a contact
information, and then showing someone a
phone number. And actually being able to
call someone was the economically
valuable
work. And again, many of this is
actually being solved by things like
query routing, introducing new tools,
extracting metadata, and sometimes a lot
of the solutions are just using long
context, right? You can use search and
have all these filters to find the right
document and then just throw everything
into long context. Like rag isn't dead,
but long context is going to be here.
It's going to be very useful. And then
lastly, just thinking about generation
prompts too. If you know what kind of
questions are coming in or you know what
kind of use cases are being import are
really important based on the context
you can even change your generation
prompts right or even to dynamically
create UI like if you know it's about
contacting people you just render the
contact card right and anthropic does
this a bunch in this example they do
this kind of data analysis over the
conversations compared to the US census
or something like that and you can see
okay well clearly if they build a coding
agent and this is over represented in
the computer science department, a
coding agent is going to crush. It's
going to do very very well. Uh I don't
know why they would do transportation
and materials moving. But generally
there's some ideas here and and actually
four hours ago they just came out with
this article on how they did data
analysis for the education product. They
were able to figure out that most of the
problem solvings were about outputs
versus problem solving and whether or
not we can identify that you know people
are using anthropic to cheat or
something like that. And they did this
and then a week later they announced the
education product. Right? This is this
is the analysis they did ahead of a
product launch. Um this is an example of
a real kind of classification I did for
a customer where we're trying to figure
out what was going on and it turns out
that uh many of the questions people
asked about was about quantifying time
spent and we just weren't able to do
that based on the way that we had
processed
information. So then we just made a SQL
light database two days later we can
answer questions like this right
sometimes the answer is a file. If it's
the answer is a file, maybe we should
let them click the file and open it,
right? If it's a, you know, time filter,
maybe we should also just render a
calendar date so we can just have them
edit it versus try to prompt again. None
of this is the AI's fault. You got to
build good software. And if you want to
think about what to cluster, what to
classify, you can do a lot of different
things, right? You can look at the
summaries of the entire conversation.
You could have embeddings and cluster
the questions people are asking if
you're building a search bar. You can
even do data analysis on the chunks that
are being retrieved or the question
types or filters and all this good
stuff. But all this is is going to allow
you to motivate a lot of the the
research and the investments you're
going to make when you build these
products, right? You can always just
talk to customers, but if you have a
million conversations, this is something
that you can process in a couple of days
rather than doing weeks of user
research. And then once you identify
these clusters and identify these
topics, then you can go talk to your
customers and figure out what is the
valuable work to be done uh with a
client. One of the things we realized
was just uh if we could identify whether
or not contracts were signed before they
were due next week, we could prevent
like $60,000 delays. And this is like 30
lines of code. We did this and we get
like thank you emails like every week,
right? I mean, they're saving more money
than they're paying me. So, it's
definitely worth it. If you want to
think about things like uh topic
modeling, you can check out a library
called BERT topic. This is kind of what
I use for a lot of this work. And if you
want to see an application of this,
check out anthropics paper on cleo
privacy preserving insights into real
world AI
use. And if you do all this, you can
kind of motivate how you think about
tools, right? Like rag is not just some
semantic search tool that you can call
that will solve everything. And in most
times, agents require a portfolio of
tools. Like even here, just recognizing
that sometimes being ex being explicit
in presenting the GP tool is much more
useful than just presenting it the
command line tool. It turns out if you
give it GP, it's going to use GP more
often and you're going to have better
tool selection. And the reason this
matters is because if you think about
the probability of finding something,
it's just these two things multiply by
each other. Probability that you find
the correct thing given the right tool
and the probability you find the right
tool. And turns out you can measure
these two individual numbers very easily
and you just work on the one that's
lower. Like that's how simple it should
feel like. Right? This is not this is
when you know that you're doing the
right thing. And if you think about the
product as a whole, it's these three
numbers you got to measure, right? It
the probability of success is basically
whether or not you choose the right
tool, whether you use the right tool
given the query, and whether or not you
give a right query. And the query is
this like nebulous UI education product
thing. Probability of success is
basically going to be your business,
right? Selecting the right tool, that's
basically going to be your retrieval
evals. And then the probability of right
tool given the query. This is basically
how good your router is. And both the
retrieval process and the router process
is a very simple binary task that's very
easy to evaluate, right? You can
evaluate thousands of these in in under
a second. It don't cost anything. And no
one's going to be doing this like
endtoend LLM eval and just asking like
wait why did we spend like $4,000 this
weekend, right? And all of this can just
be be segmented by inventory and
capabilities. And uh that's basically
it, right? The goal here is really
understanding how to measure success and
prioritizing the highest ROI work. And
that's it. If you want to talk to me,
you can just sign up here, send me an
email, or just DM me on Slack. Thank
you.
Thanks very much for that, Jason. Any
questions?
So, you built a built system.
So, the first thing I would do is just
like add some kind of like thumbs up,
thumbs down. You're basically going to
get like 1% acceptance rate, but that's
that's something. And really, your goal
is to just log every single question.
So, that's column one is just like
question text. Column two is like thumbs
up, thumbs down, or null. And that's
basically enough data to bas to
understand what's going on. Like, if you
just look at every example because you
have a thousand questions, generally
you're going to just realize something
feels weird. like uh we did this with
somebody, we just realized like, hey, we
went viral in China. Half the questions
are in Chinese. I didn't realize that.
Okay, we should go figure this out.
Another example was uh all of our
documents were indexed by calendar year,
but the questions were being asked for
like fiscal year and we just noticed
that because in December 2024, we just
saw a bunch of questions for 2025 and I
was like, "Okay, like we have to fix
this." Um, and then once you have like
10,000 questions, then you then you
segment and just do the same thing again
just recursively over and over. And the
answers usually will feel pretty obvious
like
one more question.
Well, a lot of it is just well look uh
your the job of this machine is to print
money and like 40% of the inputs are
returning nothing. So like do you want
an outcome? Right? And maybe if they say
it's not a priority then I maybe I can
believe them. But um I think because I'm
coming at it from the perspective of a
consultant um a lot of it is just going
like hey like 40% of your questions are
like asking people's schedules and we
don't have that data. So we can either
say let's let's say we can't do it and
kind of like annoy 40% of the the
inputs. I mean maybe that's okay. Maybe
this is just an education thing or if
you care about your customers this is
clearly something to work on, right?
Because if if it if it came out to be
4%, I would tell you not to worry about
it. But it's 40 and you can make this
decision of whether or not you want to
like have better customer satisfaction.
But 40% is a lot. We should do
something. And that is the reason we do
this because we have those numbers,
right? It's like 40% has a 10% success
rate. Your choice. It's not really
subjective anymore.
All right. I think we're going to stop
the Q&A now. Feel free to catch up with
Jason later on after the talks. Let's
hear it again. Thanks very much, Jason.
Right. So our next speaker is Anuk
Mouse. Uh Anuk is a solutions engineer
at Open AI where she works on some of
the largest enterprises across Europe to
help them adopt and integrate AI into
their workflows. She previously led
customer engagement and engineering
teams at Google Cloud and has a
background in data analytics and AI.
having lived and worked in London,
Amsterdam, and Hong Kong. She brings
grounded experience in making AI useful
across different industries and
cultures. Uh I think we're just
finishing up the the setup and then
we'll be ready to make a start. Thank
you.
Excellent. So, thank you for your time.
um delighted to
uh be here and speak to you a little bit
about something that um we at OpenAI
recently launched the agent SDK. Um I'm
an solutions engineer at OpenAI usually
work with our enterprises as you heard.
[Music]
Um and before we kick off I want to take
a little look back at where we were a
year ago. So I think 2024, this time of
year, we were very much uh all figuring
out how we could best prompt engineer
and how could we get most out of our
models. But if we wanted to stitch
something together into a little bit
more of a dynamic workflow, um tool use,
uh memory, multi-step logic, uh it got
pretty complicated pretty quick. uh
prompt injection risks, um passing
around uh context, parsing outputs,
wiring up
APIs. Uh it was all doable, but it very
much felt like glue code. Fast forward
to 2025, think we're moving to a much
more modular uh environment. We have a
lot of tools for orchestration. The
agents SDK, which I'll talk about today,
is one of those. Um, and it really helps
you sort of uh it starts to feel as a
developer like we're working with uh
building blocks rather than duct tape,
which is fantastic. And I think uh
adding in MCP, which we'll hear more
about uh later today, is really going to
add to that and uh allowing us to sort
of work from registries that we have
there. Taking a step back, why do
agentic workflows matter? I think real
world problems when we were sort of
doing that prompt engineering uh when we
were doing those sort of prompt
engineering
questions real world problems are never
single step it's never um when someone
wants to book something when you have a
customer support request coming in uh
whatever you're building real life
situations are context dependent they
require statefulness uh they need memory
and um you need to sort of turn the next
step based on that intermediate outcome
that we're
finding. And why is that hard? Because
we're stitching together planning loops.
Um we're writing we were writing tools
by hand, I think, for a long time. There
was a lot of uh manual work there. And I
don't know if any of you have been
debugging
um um enormous sort of spaghetti uh JSON
prompt flows, but it's not a fun thing
to be working on. Uh and when you do get
issues or you do want to iterate and
optimize,
uh you're basically stuck. There's no
way to deal with traceability
easily. This is, I think, where tools
like the agent SDK that I want to show
you today um really help. It allows you
to uh simply have Python functions that
you can decorate with a function tool.
It deals with all that orchestration for
you. Um, and I think one of the most
exciting things for me at least is that
you can have that tracing and debugging
in a very elegant
UI. It also deals with multi-agent
handoffs and we'll talk in a moment
about why multi- aent is so important.
Um, and I think one of the things that
I'm excited about today is the full uh
native integration with
MCP. So, what exactly did we
launch just over uh just under a month
ago? Um, we launched a new tool set for
building
agents. And the agents platform really
is a set of different components um that
work seamlessly together, but are also
modular. So you can sort of pick and
choose whatever works uh for your
development flow and it's all built on
uh the runtime environments really the
responses API which is uh a multi-step
uh stateful API that
um allows you that that's wrapped into
the agents SDK and that agents SDK as I
mentioned has a lot of um elegant uh
tracing UI and and platform around it
but it also comes with three built-in
tools. And three tools doesn't sound
like a lot, but I think they're they're
quite powerful. One, the first one is uh
web search. So, sort of allowing you
might have fantastic uh rack solution,
but you also want that up-to-date
information. Um so, it allows your
products and and your customers to work
with their data, which we get to through
file search. That can be like their CRM,
like whatever legacy systems there are.
Um and mix that with with the latest
information. And then the last thing
that's uh coming built in is a computer
using agent. And I don't know if any of
you have worked with um the uh with
operator. I see show of
hands. That's not a lot. So let me show
you uh a little example of what uh
operator looks like. So operator is
effectively a way of rather than
plugging into any other systems through
an AI, it's using your computer like a
human would. Um so this is the interface
looks a lot like a chat GBT interface.
And what I asked it is uh can you find
some popular open source MCP tools on
GitHub and then summarize uh the key
setup and installation instructions and
capabilities and created them in a new
doc called uh MCP tool cheat sheet.
And what that looks like if we have a
quick look is basically
um the tool then takes over of my
browser. So let's quickly play
that. I'm doing nothing here. And what
happens? It uh does a web search. It
finds a git repository that it likes.
It's going through it. It's clicking
around. It's finding uh initially a
Spanish speaking Spanish language
installation guide. It knows that I
don't speak English because it has my
context. So, it's actually going to find
for the localization of the English
version of it. And once it finds it, um
it's going to find a way to put that in
a document. Now, you can give it the
permissions to integrate with uh your
Google Docs, for example, and have it
create that. In this case, it finds a
web tool because I haven't given it any
permissions. But I think the real unlock
here having that out of the box is when
you're dealing with uh more legacy
customers for example who have tools
that don't have API endpoints that are
not easy to integrate with you're sort
of unlocking working with those systems
and getting information out of
that. So that's a little bit on the on
the computer using agent. That's one of
the tools that's built into the
responses API. And by the way um Jason
just mentioned deep research. The
responses API is really what's at the
basis of that deep research product as
well. What I'm excited about today is
that the agents SDK is uh fully open
sourced and it supports um third party
models as well. So any of the models
that you're using, any combination that
you're leveraging, you can swap out the
brain and still use the tools.
So, back to our agentic workflow. I
think if we're going to one agent, um
here we see an example of a reservation
agent, something that can make a booking
for me. Starts with a user input,
usually voice or
text. Um goes to the agent and that has
uh the model and its routine. And based
on the routine, in this case, I've told
it uh help the user make a booking. And
so I might ask it um I want a
hairdresser appointment coming
Monday. Based on the routine and my
input, it knows uh sort of like it has
four tools in this case. So it might
check my calendar, pick a slot that
works, then goes to the booking
appointment tool of the hairdresser. It
will complete the information with a
separate tool and then um it might
summarize all of that and sends it back
in a text to me. Uses the user
confirmation tool for that.
pretty straightforward so far. I think
where this um sometimes falls down is
that we can be tempted to give one agent
way too many
tools and when we do that um you get pro
problems like prompt overflow. Um your
system like the behavior often comes a
bit erratic or at least less
predictable. And so the way to scale
this is through a network of agents. So
the input still looks the same voice or
text coming in. We have the model. Now
the first routine sits with a triage
agent. And based on my input, based on
the request I have, it's going to choose
where do I hand off to? Like what agent
am I using? And I think what we're um
achieving here is a much clearer uh
intent to tooling. So because an agent
has a much narrower scope, it's going to
be much more predictable in which tool
it picks. Um you're going to have way
more compact and purposeful prompts. So
that makes uh all your systems cheaper
and faster. You're using um less token
throughput and it's really going to help
you in uh debugging and uh observing
because now you can sort of check in
which agent things are going wrong. It
also helps with scaling and iteration
uh because you can swap out individual
agents one at a
time. So what I want to show you is an
example of what one of those flows look
like and specifically I want to focus on
what that tracing platform and the UI
there uh looks like because I think that
will really I think that's a big unlock
uh from a development perspective.
So I have a very simple agent here that
helps me. Um there's only a gentle
platform. There's only two agents and
this is uh for Patagonia the company and
I'm uh connecting to it as a
customer. Hi there. I'm um looking for
some information about my orders.
So what it's going to do, you can see
it. I can help with that. What specific
information do you need about your
orders? So you can see it started with a
triage agent and the first step that it
took is it transferred to the customer
support agent. From a user perspective,
I don't notice anything.
Um, can you tell me what my last order
was specifically? Which color?
This is the ultimate insult when you
have English as a second language. It's
switching to my native language now, but
I'll translate. Um, it's basically
telling me that my last order was on
February 9th and it was a pair of uh
green shorts, olive green. Um, do I have
other questions? So, what you see it's
it's choosing one of its tools, but I've
limited to this customer support agent
the number of tools I give it. And rule
of thumb, um, we tend to say max 20
tools an agent. That's where you really
start seeing the performance going down
if you go over that.
Um, yeah. I really like the green
shorts, but uh they don't go well with
my recent uh jacket that I bought. Uh,
the order number was
AD620. Can I cancel that,
please? I've successfully cancelled your
order jacket
number. Let me know if there's else you
need. Well, that's a double win. First
of all, it processed my refund and
second of all, it spoke English to me
again.
Um, so that's a pretty straightforward
uh interaction, I think. But you can see
it supports voice natively. Um, it's
it's worked with this. But the cool
thing is is now the traces platform that
I want to show you. So, this comes out
of the box with the agent SDK. And if I
now look at my traces, this is sort of
all the interactions I've had today. And
this is the last conversation we had.
And what this gives me is a visual
stepby-step guide of what went on in
this conversation. So I can see that I'm
landing at the triage agent. I can see
um all the details here. I can see that
it's handing off uh to the support
agent. Um but if I look at
um what's posted, I even actually have
the snippets here. Sure, I can help with
that. So I can listen back to what the
agent is. I can listen back to what the
user said. Um I have the transcriptions
of that. Uh I see all the handoffs. So I
think that's where the real unlock comes
of um scaling faster and
iterating. So in short, what the agent
SDK gives you is a super simple and
lightweight way um to uh create those
multi- aent workflows in any situation.
Um it has that tracing built in and I
think most importantly um it allows you
uh for optimization
faster.
Um from an observer yeah you can um
again this works out of the box uh with
the SDK and on any model. So you can
whatever models you're using today you
can leverage this
on. And I think what's exciting for uh
what we'll hear after this, it uh fully
allows integration with MCP servers. Um
it can connect that local or uh remote.
Zero manual wiring required. Uh and you
can also call uh the list tools to
basically get your agents to discover
whatever uh new tools are uh published
in the the MCP service that you're
working with.
I think the last thing that's important
to mention is um this is not just
experimentation at this point. We have
uh many customers that are already uh
using that agents SDK in production.
Lumini is one that are use working with
a lot of legacy legal customers. For
example, they're the computer use agent
that we spoke about is really important
because they have a lot of those legacy
systems that you just cannot get access
to um through an API. Coinbase built
agent kit which uh lets AI uh agents
connect with crypto wallets uh take
actions uh on chain and box is using
that combination of web search and file
search that you get out of the box. Um
so I'd highly recommend uh it's open
source try out the SDK if you want the
references that I've shared here and uh
the resources uh the decks available at
this QR code. So, um, have a look at
that. Have some questions. Keen to hear
if you've already worked with this or
not. Uh, and if so, would love your
feedback. Um, but that's what I wanted
to share with you today. Thank you very
much. Thank you very much, Shan, for
that excellent talk. We've got time for
perhaps two questions. I'm going to try
and repeat the questions for the
recording. Uh,
question is about how reusable agents
are across two different applications.
Uh how's the handoff?
I think it really depends. I think you
do find processes. If I think about um a
very common like flow that has a lot of
agents uh in workflow that we see a lot
dayto-day is uh a customer service
workflow. Now if you take a triage agent
that basically needs to take the initial
um customer input and sort of just
recognize what other agents do I have in
my
network. That's often quite reusable. If
you have something that is about a very
specific part of your customer journey,
uh, where you've written that routine to
be like very niche tools, it's probably
going to be harder. But I think like the
further left, like the more common that
step is in the customer journey or in
the interaction, the more reusable
you'll find it.
Does the model?
It depends what you want to do. Sorry,
I'll just repeat the question. The
question is, does the model have to be
multimodal or can you use any sort of
model? If you No, if you have texton
models, that's totally fine. It
obviously limits the the type of use
cases that you can do with it. Um, but
but no, any model uh is supported.
Doesn't have to be multimodal.
Thank you. Thank you very much.
Next we have Samuel Golden. Samuel is
the creator of the Pyantic data
validation library which is downloaded
300 million times per month. I think
most people here are familiar with it.
uh two years ago he founded the
pideantic company uh which continues to
maintain the pyantic validation library
and more recently uh has been building
pyantic AI been having some good chats
with people about that this evening and
pantic AI is an agent framework which is
rapidly gaining popularity pantic is
also building logfire a comprehensive
observability platform that offers both
general purpose observability and also
specialized capabilities purpose-built
for AI applications over Over to you,
Samuel. Thank you very much. Um, yeah,
that was a great intro. You've kind of
covered the first thing I was going to
talk about. Uh, I'm going to be really
quick tonight because I know we haven't
got that much time, but um, yeah, I'm
going to assume that if you've managed
to get here and haven't heard of
Pyantic, then that's kind of like
willful ignorance. So, but but obviously
the rest of what we're doing in terms of
Pantic AI and Logfire maybe less so. So,
how many people here have heard of I'm
not going to go through it all, but
Pantic AI and or Logfire? Okay. So, so a
fair number, but maybe not so many of
you have used it. So, uh I'm going to
I'm going to start with Padantic AI,
although we actually built it more more
recently. Come the tail end of last
year, we were well or I in particular
was very proud of how widely paid was
being used in Genai. It was obviously
used in OpenAI and Anthropics SDK,
Google's SDK and in all the agent
frameworks. I was perhaps less proud of
the engineering quality of most of those
agent frameworks when I came to try and
use them. And so I kind of started this
this project to see what it would look
like to build an agent framework that
was production ready, that was type
safe, that was properly properly unit
tested. Lots of other things that you
would have taken for granted with most
popular Python libraries turned out not
to be the case with with agent
frameworks. And so padantic AI was was
what came out. Um, and more recently
we've added MCP support. So I'm going to
talk through a very brief very tiny
example of an agent uh here. And
obviously I have the logfire
integration. So I'll show you it running
within Logfire. Um so we have the the
agent imported from Pinance AI. We're
obviously importing Logfire and we're
going to use an MCP server. So MCP can
work in two different ways effectively
as a subprocess uh which is referred to
as standard IO or as over HTTP. Uh here
I'm going to run uh the MCP server as a
subprocess. Um hence why I've imported
this this uh data class. And then I'm
going to configure logfire. I'm going to
instrument uh I'm going to configure it
to use a local environment variable to
send data to my project. I'm going to
instrument MCP. So that is not specific
to Pantic AI. You can use that to
instrument any MCP client or server in
Python. And I'm obviously going to
instrument pantic AI our library. Then
I'm going to define the MCP server I'm
going to use. In this case, it's
Microsoft's MCP server for playright. So
this effectively allows us to do uh
browser control um using a local local
playwright instance local
um uh Chrome browser is going to is
going to uh operate. I'm defining my
agent here. I'm doing very very little
here. I'm just saying I'm going to use
anthropic um and I'm going to define the
MCP servers I'm going to use. I could
also say I want to return a different
data type here. So, by default, an agent
will return a string, but I could also
uh return some other data. I'll show you
in a minute. Um, and then when it come
to run our code, we're going to start
our MCP servers. So, they're going to
run for the duration of this agent. You
can imagine if this was uh a fast API
app, for example, you would probably run
this within your life cycle function so
that the MCP servers would run for the
duration of your app. Then, I'm just
going to run the agent with a prompt.
And in particular, I'm going to ask it
to go to our website uh find the uh
recent blog post and then uh extract the
announcements from that and and bring
them out and thereby force you to look
at recent announcements we've made
without just reading through uh a web
page. Um but just to show um like I say
obviously the thing we're known for is
data validation and returning structured
data from LMS and that is obviously
something that paid particularly well.
So if we look here uh we'll see the data
type returned is is a string but if we
wanted to change that we can do result
type and let's say we wanted to return
list of strings in the sense that we're
returning a list of summaries. Uh the
data type here both in terms of static
typing and in terms of what we're
guaranteed to get out from the runtime
type checking of pyantic will be a list
of strings. I'll stick in this case to a
string because it displays a little
better. And then lastly down here I'm
just going to run it. So if I Nope, I
don't want that at all. If I come and
run uh not that example, but this
example here, um we'll see uh the agent
start to run calling claw deciding what
to do, listing MTP servers, sorry,
listing the functions from the MCP
server, listing uh tools, and then it
should in a moment open Chrome and start
to go and make those requests. So you
will see Chrome has opened and it's
going to go and uh navigate through our
website to hopefully go and find the
blog if we're lucky and um get that list
of articles sorry list of announcements.
But you can see in the background this
is logfire. This is my logfire project
and so you can see the agent running
here uh and you can see those same
things happening but we can see the
duration of the different requests. So
we're using claw 3.7 which is a
relatively heavy model. So, it's taken
13 seconds here to decide what to do.
It's then gone and used the MCP
server. It's used the browser navigate
function to go to pantic.dev correctly.
The MCP tool has returned in this case a
kind of summary of the page uh which has
then been returned to the model here
where we've called uh Claude again. And
lastly, we made a final browser click in
this case to get the articles. Um, oh
no, it's still running.
Uh, and then fingers crossed it's at
some point going to finish and we'll be
able to see with a bit of luck the
output. So you see, come back over here,
we have the output from logfire as it's
running those traces, but obviously much
more detail here within the logfire UI.
Um, and so it should now have finished.
And so we can see the full uh output of
the uh run within within logfire. So you
can see we had the user message saying
uh what we wanted to do the assistant
talking to itself about what it's going
to go and do calling the tool getting
the result back from the tool and back
and forth. And finally here you can see
it's returned that summary of
announcements we've made recently. So,
pyantic evals uh eval library MCP
support within logfire which I'm not
demoing today. Um new SDKs in JavaScript
and in Rust enterprise uh Logfire
enterprise uh what it's described as
platform improvements and then uh
release of Pantic 211 which it's calling
uh core framework updates. But obviously
the nice thing I'm I'm just using the
Logfire UI to tell you what we've done
recently. But obviously the power here
comes from not only is Logfire AI
specific observability which is what I'm
using it for solely here but it's also
general purpose observability platform
built on open telemetry logs traces and
metrics able to scale up to tens of
millions of spans an hour. Um and
therefore the the reality is as Jason
was saying earlier AI doesn't exist in a
vacuum. It exists within other
applications. the things that cause it
to go wrong are not always my prompt
isn't set up right. It is that my
database credentials are wrong or my
query is illconfigured or whatever it
might be. And that's where Logfire being
a general purpose observability platform
really comes into its own as opposed to
the other AI observability platforms
which are only offering you the the AI
view as it were. So just to to summarize
this particular call you can see here we
have the we also have costs. So we can
see that this particular run cost us a
total of 9 cents to go off and and get
the list of outputs.
Um and yeah just just one other thing to
say here we're we're the tracing here
we're seeing uh the the tool being
called by panici but this this span here
MCP request where we have the details of
the back and forth with the MCP server.
This is just our MCP integr uh
instrumentation. So you can go and use
that whether or not you're using uh
pantic AI and you'll see when we
um yeah we printed out the output at the
end of our run. So we got the same same
output here. Um,
another key component sort of following
on uh from what's being said earlier
about uh agents is that in reality
simple agents like this where you do
effectively a kind of one well it's not
one shot in the sense it's done a lot of
back and forth internally but in your
code a single agent being called is a
kind of minority of cases and in reality
we want more
uh control over exactly what's going to
go on. So this uh this code is doing
effectively exactly the same thing.
We're using the same MCP server. Um
we've got a similar agent. We've given
it a system prompt and some MCP servers.
The difference here is we're using
pideantic graph which is part of pyantic
AI which gives us uh finite state
machine
functionality. I suspect if you asked
any academic who had any opinions about
graphs and finite state machines that
they would be appalled by what we're
calling graphs here. It's really a way
of executing your code which makes it
easy to separate individual components
and therefore to one run them
distributed over space and time because
you're snapshotting between each piece
of code that's run and two go and look
at what went wrong. So in this
particular graph we have we have a find
blog uh node which is going to go and
use the the browser agent
um to to get back to effectively go find
me the URL of the list of blogs and then
we call um the get post HTML node which
is defined here. Now what's unusual and
well unique about pyantic graph is we
use as we use type annotations in
pyantic itself to define data structures
we use type annotations to define the
structure of our graph so we haven't got
some horrible add edge function further
on down which is which connects uh find
blog to get post HTML the type
annotization itself is defining the the
structure of our graph and so if we
returned the wrong type here we would
immediately get a type checking error we
can confirm just by just by running
static type checking over our code that
our graph's execution at least uh uh in
terms of its typing is consistent with
the structure of our graph. Um and so we
have a third node here summarize the
content which is going to go and and
summarize uh this content and our graph
in this case is very simple. It's just
those three nodes. One of the other neat
things we get out of running
um of defining and stuff like this is we
can go and build mermaid diagrams for
our um for our graphs very easily. Um
it's not very exciting. So it's not the
it's not the most useful thing, but it's
definitely worthwhile. In this
particular case, if I run this, we're
going to get the most boring graph
imaginable. Uh that looks like this. Um,
but you imagine that in in much more
complex situations where you're
connecting multiple different agents
together, this this can be useful. Um,
but in particular, if we we get rid of
that, am I going to be brave enough to
run this one? I wrote this while I was
waiting for the other talk. So, this may
go wrong. We may be demonstrating uh
logfire's capacity to debug and to show
exceptions. Um, but we'll try it and see
what happens. Um, so we see we're in the
first uh node here. So, if we come back
over and I close that, we should
have, is it running? It should be over
here.
Um, oh, we got the browser opening and
we got that first node, uh, find blog
running and it will go and hopefully
find the the URL. The powerful thing
about separating out our tasks like this
is that if we have an error, we can go
and look at where it was and try and
improve that particular bit. Whereas if
we have a singleshot agent doing
something really complicated, if it
doesn't if it works, great. If it
doesn't work, how do we go about
improving it? How do we go about
snapshotting it and and uh continuing
from a previous point? One of the neat
things about graphs is you can, as I
say, snapshot between each node
execution. So, it's a bit like playing a
computer game where you can basically
load from where where you last saved and
try the boss again if you got killed.
Whereas that's not the case with like
general execution. Um, and so you look
at top level, we've run our three nodes
and see if it was able to get anything
remotely useful out of the
bottom.
Uh, if we look at Okay, so it got given
a bunch of HTML and it's done a
reasonable job of getting out the same
output. How am I doing for time? Have I
got one more example or are we pushing
it? Okay, I'll do one more quick
example. Um this is a another uh MCP
server an MCP server that we actually
maintain within Pinantic AI which allows
us to run sandbox Python code. So it's
very often very valuable to be able to
ask uh a model to go and run code rather
than do calculations itself because one
models are like notoriously unreliable
at doing calculations and two if we have
the Python code that is used to do a
calculation we can go back and audit if
you get the right result that it was
actually the right calculation and if
you didn't what it might have done
wrong. We can also build coding agents
where we basically allow the AI to
define the code that result that is uh
the foundation of the agent. We haven't
got all of that built in. But anyway,
I'll show you this example quickly. And
again, we've built this as an MCP server
rather than building it as a tool
particularly for Pyantic AI. So you can
go and use it whether or not you're
using Pyantic AI. It's just an MCP
server. So we're going to run it with
Dino this time rather than NPX because
Dino has isolation. give a bunch of
configuration to Dino to tell it how to
do the isolation and then we run our MTP
server run Python code MTP server and
again we run it in standard IO mode um
and we're going to ask it a very simple
uh question in this case how long would
it take to travel yada yada yada and we
are using in this case open AAI just to
be different and if we go and run that
uh this should hopefully be much quicker
uh And sure enough, it's gone and given
us a number out. And that's great. But
was it actually right? Let's go and look
at what actually happened inside the
run. And we see the the code that was
uh where am I seeing? Um maybe I'll go
in here and I'll show you within the run
the code that we actually ran on the
remote MCP server. So we can check that
this looks correct, which indeed it
does. Uh and therefore we can like
validate our output. Um, so that's a
very quick whiz through a little bit of
what Pantic AI and what Logfire can do.
I probably have time for maybe one or
two questions. Yep. That's uh Thanks
very much,
Samuel. Any
questions? Yeah.
question is what have been the hardest
challenges to display debugging and
errors to users. Um, so we are very keen
on using open standards. That's why
we've embraced MCP. That's why we've
built logfire on top of open telemetry.
That's why we allow you to write SQL to
go and query your data because we think
not only does that mean there's less for
us to build, but there's less for you to
trust us on. as in if you go and use
pyanci you don't need to trust logfire
is going to be around because we're just
emitting open telemetry. Open telemetry
however has some limitations. So it
won't give you information about a trace
until after it has finished. That's
because it was designed for an era when
it was assuming requests were going to
take 200 300 maybe 400 milliseconds and
they were going to h be happening
remotely for the most part. You didn't
care about seeing what what was going on
within them even if there were hundreds
of spans within them before they
finished. In AI that's not the case. you
show you show I showed you a a call here
that took what like I can't remember how
long it took but like uh should 84
seconds if I'm debugging it's really
useful to go and see to be able to see
that. So we've basically done some stuff
inside open telemetry to send
information about a trace as it's going
on so that we can display it on screen.
So it's been lots of walking the line
between using open standards but abusing
them where we have to to go and do uh to
to give you the best user experience if
that makes sense. That's a like tiny
example but I can give more later. Got
time for one more.
Yep.
Question is log fire can also be used as
an MCP server. Is there anything missing
in using it as our long-term memory?
That's not what it's built for. You're
right in a sense that in ultimately it's
just a database that you can go and run
SQL against to query your data. Of
course, go and try it, but like we're
we're prioritizing building an
observability platform that can do
analytics. So our use case for that MCP
server is much more connect cursor and
we have demos of this actually working.
You connect cursor to logfire. You tell
cursor please fix this bug. It will go
and query uh logfire with SQL work out
what the exception was and then go and
fix fix the bug in a way that one of the
weird things was we decided to build on
top of SQL two years ago. I wish that I
could claim to have the precience to be
like SQL will be great because we will
have MCP or its equivalent in the future
and this will allow models sorry agents
to go and like query observability data.
I didn't we were just really lucky. But
think five or 10 years in the head
ahead. What's going to be looking at
your observability data? Is it going to
be engineers or is it going to be for a
great part agents or AI? I suspect it's
going to be AI to a great extent. And
that's where that SQL view rather than
some kind of click ops query builder is
going to be so powerful.
All right. Once again, thank you Samuel.
Thank you very much.
All right, for our last lightning talk
of the evening, delighted to introduce
David Surya. David is a member of
technical staff at Anthropic and he is
the co-creator of the model context
protocol that we've been talking about a
lot this evening. His extensive
background in open source includes core
contributions to PHP where he led the
official releases of PHP 5.4 and 5.5 as
well as significant development on
mccurial. Previously, David spent nearly
a decade at Facebook, starting as a
software engineer on the developer
infrastructure team before advancing to
leadership positions. After serving as
an entrepreneur in residence at Sutter
Hill Ventures, he joined Anthropic in
April of 2024. This evening, his talk is
titled Model Context Protocol Recap and
what's
next. Over to you, David.
Hello. So, let's see that we can make
this work. um in a way that uh I do not
leak information and we shall probably
start from slide one
um common
problems. Cool. Uh yeah, I'm David. Um I
want to talk about my little side
project called the model context
protocol. Um that has been gained a
little bit of popularity recently.
Um and I'm quite happy um that out of
this uh little thing we started not even
a year ago
uh has found quite a bit of adoption. Um
but today I I do a few things. I didn't
know you know how much people know about
the protocol at first. Um so I'm going
to quickly talk about what is MCP from
my perspective. Um some of the things
that um that I wish people would do a
little bit more. I uh briefly talk about
agents in MCP and then talk about really
what's what's next for MCP
um in a very brief overview. So in the
next you know two three months and then
whoever who knows what's happening in a
year from now in AI um and then we have
a little bit of a Q&A. Um, this is I
just want to start off by a very typical
interaction I had with MCP is that most
people look at this and go like WTF? Um,
why why would I want this? And then
usually like a few days
later they come around and go like oh
this is quite quite nice actually. Um
that's been uh one of the many instances
that we have seen actually funny enough
first internally and now see this
externally happening over and over
again. Um but what is MCP? Uh MCP is you
know first and foremost an open protocol
um between AI agents uh or like or AI
applications
um and uh tools and data sources. And I
want to be very clear here um about a
few things that are have highlighted.
The first part being it's an open
protocol. The first part being uh open
which means that this is truly like
something that is really under the MIT
license. There's we can talk about this
later a lot of thought uh going into
potential future governance things
around this but it's something that
everybody's free to adopt um in any form
or shape as you like uh and use as much
as possible. Um, second is a protocol. I
talk about this in a second as to what
uh is the bit about the protocol piece
and how it solves what I would consider
like an M2M challenge. Um, but most
importantly I want to talk about the
part that this is actually a protocol
not for models which a lot of people get
wrong. They're going to be like but does
this work with uh the OpenI models? Um,
and uh, of course it does because it's
not a problem not a protocol between the
models for the models. It's a protocol
between the applications themselves um
and context providers um that go beyond
just tools which is the second part I
want to talk about. And so what does
this mean um with the protocol piece is
that about a um a year ago if you were
to go and build um an AI application or
if you were try to solve a specific part
of um of of of a problem with an LLM,
you were uh usually faced with one of
two options. The first one being you
either go and build this yourself and
probably reinvent another chat
application that looks very similar to
uh chat GPT desktop or uh cloud desktop
um just probably a little bit shittier
um or um uh you were um relying on the
custom integrations that these tools
provided for you without any or very
specific opportunities
um to extend that for uh yourself. Um
you could, you know, use a very unique
thing that was existed at the time uh
extensions for um uh Copilot for
example, but they were very unique to
that specific thing. And so what you
ended up with is for every application
you would uh use, you had to build a
custom integration. That's sort of like
for n applications, you have to build m
um integrations. And that's a lot of
effort. And this is a very classic
problem that you see over and over
again. Uh and in fact, one of the major
inspirations for creating MCP was a
protocol called LSP, which I'm sure you
all use. You might not know necessarily
about it, but it's what usually drives
um the language servers under the hood
of your IDE to inform the IDE about um
you know, type hinting, type
information, these type of things. And
if you look back in our um uh and have
seen the world before these things were
around, every IDE had to implement their
own uh integrations for a language. And
what it ended up with is that all the ID
integrators had to go and um focus a lot
of time of implementing things for a
language um instead of focusing on
actually improving the ID integr like
the IDE itself. And at the same time um
every um integration for a language was
slightly shitty in their own specific
way for an IDE. And with LSP coming
around um basically everybody's like
could focus on one LS like integration
um to make this really really good and
the IDE people could finally uh focus on
only building a great IDE and just
everybody was happier off and I think
this is a very similar approach here
where you now with something like MCP
you can build one integration that is
really really good and use it across a
wide variety of applications including
um like customuilt things on top of
agent framework like uh pedantici
Um, and so this is really what this is
trying to solve. It's like this MTON
problem. Um, and and part of that
problem in in the specific instance that
I saw uh that really led to the creation
of the protocol was that I got really um
fed up by copying stuff in and out of
cloud desktop between Zet and Claw
Desktop which was you know the editor of
choice of the time and I was just like
there should be a better way of doing
this and protocols are one way to solve
these. So nowadays, you know, people can
focus on building one great integration.
Um, so for example, if you ever want to
use a GitHub server, uh, you don't have
to build your own custom GitHub
integration. You just use the one that,
uh, they provide because they probably
have people on staff and paid for that.
And and that makes usually, not always,
for a better experience. And then you
plug this into uh, whatever MCP client
you you
fancy. Um, um, and so how does this
actually work? Um the there is what MCP
actually is. It's it's the most it's a
it's a specification. It's a very it's a
set of boring text that specify how this
MCP client needs to talk to the MCP
server a common language between each
other. And it defines three uh
primitives at least actually does way
more than that. Um out of which sadly
mostly only one is used which is the
tools. Um but there is more to that. Um
there is more to MCP in general. Um
there's a thing called resources that
MCP clients can ask for uh and MCP
servers can expose. There's something
called tools obviously that everyone is
currently using because it's really what
makes you feel the like I feel the LLM
magic in kind of like in the best
possible way. Um and then there's
something called prompt templates uh
which which also very few clients
implement and uh very few MCP servers uh
implement. Um and and those are the the
three big primitives that servers can
expose as a form of data sources um or
like as a form of like data that an LLM
application can use. Um, and the the way
these are supposed to be used, uh, the
way we envisioned this is that prompt
templates are really like something a
user drives and like a chat application
to insert like a template for example
that knows how to best deal with with
these tools or that um, you know, even
like already like uh, gives you like
downloads you some data that might be
useful, but that you might want to edit
in in advance. Um resources are are more
like you know files that you can attach
um to to to applications. Um and uh but
also like a more gen general like data
pipeline between the two um and
something I will talk about bit later
that I wish people would do more uh is
use resources as one way to abstract
rack um pipeline inputs and then there's
of course tools that everybody's using
uh today. There are two way main ways of
how you can uh use MCP um servers at the
moment. One is local. So this is like
really the the onetoone equivalent to
how um language servers would work. They
would you know start be start local and
talk um what is apparently surprisingly
to most people not to my mind but
apparently a lot of people's mind uh a
rather complicated uh way called uh just
standard in standard out. Um so the the
the client starts the process and talks
to that uh process um over standard
instant out. Um a great example that I
really loved using very early and I
still love using is um it allows me to
build my own integrations for the things
I care about on my laptop. And so for
example, I have a Postgress database
locally on a Docker container. And no
matter like if without MCP, there would
be a no world where any applications I
care about would implement a local
database connector um this year at least
um to my local Posgress database. But
now with MTP I can go build that
integration myself and I can have um my
cursor my cloud desktop um and other MCP
clients go and chat to that Postgress
database locally and you know visualize
my database um look at uh query the
database in funny ways uh and do a lot
of other things and I can get very
creative with these type of things and I
think I'm not sure um how much you uh
you follow this but people have gotten
very creative with these local MCP
servers to the point where they control
Blender, they control um uh one of the
funniest things I still find one of the
funniest things someone who just hooked
it up to their Amazon account and had
Amazon buy all their uh Christmas gifts
that way uh or had Claude buy all the
Christmas gifts um we an MCP server and
so this enables a lot of like you
building for yourself and really making
that little bit of magic happen that I
feel we saw in these initial tweets of
like I can actually make an LLM do
things that I have taugh taught it to do
and not have to wait for some company to
come around and tell me how it's done,
right? And I feel that's a lot of the
magic that people really see when they
see MCP and actually use
it. And now currently we're I think in a
phase where uh some second part happens
where there's a second part to the
protocol where the transport is going to
remote servers. And so this means
instead of having something locally
running, which is probably the by far
the vast majority of the roughly 4,000
MCP servers that we currently have uh or
that I have seen like across uh
registries, it's very hard to keep track
of it. Um and um and we have a second
protocol uh transport that is basically
focused on uh doing this to over the
web. And so what this means is that now
SAS companies can build integrate or any
company data providers can build MCP
servers and host MCP servers on their
platform like you can imagine an
MCP.github.com or you can already have
for example an
MCP.appal.com and they now and you can
hook these up to your application now
you can talk to your PayPal account to
your GitHub account and you don't have
to run the thing locally anymore. uh you
go to them uh and you authorize with
your account there and you go and be
able to um to make use of that data
inside an LLM application and I think
that's a different very different
perspective. It goes away from this like
local hacker ability that we have with
local MCP servers and it's quite
beautiful in a way to like really like
empowering like a whole like um you know
new industry paradigma like how you
actually go talk between lamps and like
um remote data sources. Um, and so I
think that's quite cool and something
that we're currently seeing popping up
because we just
finalized with one or two changes
probably pending uh authorization um and
uh and have a have a more stateless
protocol um uh transport. Um so that's
really happening now and a lot of
companies look into that.
Um I added this two minutes ago.
Um things a random things I wish people
would do more um use prompts uh use
resources and use notifications
um to to really enrich the uh the
application and go beyond just p pure
tool calling in MCP. I wish people would
experiment more with something called
sampling. I will go into the details of
what this is. uh and I wish u more IDE
providers and I'm very happy to see that
uh VS code actually is the one of the
first ones besides cloud code um that
supports this a feature called roots
which basically just allows MCP servers
to look up um when you are talking to an
IDE which are the projects you currently
have open so if you want to build a git
server a git MCP server and want to know
which is the repository actually should
talk to you kind of want to know what is
actually opening cursor and so that's
one way to to tell um that agents I will
quickly talk about and then I wish
people would more contribute. Um this is
really an open source project. A lot of
the things that I started my career with
is by uh contributing to PHP by
contributing to mur contributing to git
and by just not being afraid to be
engaged uh with one of these projects.
Um and of course not always but you know
sometimes you might be uh you might uh
get your PR uh uh refused and sometimes
you might have changes requested. Um I
the only thing I can promise you um uh
unlike uh when I started I will never
call anybody an idiot. Um at least I
hope so. I might think it. Um cool. So
let's talk a bit about agents. Um that's
been the talk of the day. Okay. Uh so I
just want to briefly talk a bit about
agents and MCP and something fun you can
do and I something fun that uh I don't
know where this leads us but it's a
quite an interesting experimentation
that we experimented quite early with
and I think that has a lot of promise
particularly if you combine them with
different agent frameworks um such as
the openi one or or pentatic
um and that is the idea like if you you
take like some sort of like agent
systems to a system that like
dynamically directs their own process
and tool usage or or something like a
workflowy the thing that um where an LLM
and uh tools are orchestrated through a
predefined code path um uh and um you
want to build something along that line
which is how these agents tend to look
like you know you will require some form
of retrieval you will require some form
of tools for an agent and you will some
form of memory in the long run so make
these things some somewhat stateful have
some externalities like things that they
can call out to and have some form of
retrieval uh and I heard um someone uh
sells apparently very good courses on
how you do retrieval really well. Um
which I might have to sign up to. Um and
and one thing that is very interesting
and this is really the the really fun
part. Um if you get nothing out of this
uh this is the this is the fun bit that
I think people do not know much about
MCP. So you probably might know a lot
about MCP but this you might not know.
There's a little little feature called
sampling in MCP. And when people look at
sampling, they also often go like, what
the heck is this and why would I care?
Um, but sampling is an interesting bit
that we usually originally built into
the protocol for the reason that the
protocol should be model independent. So
what does this mean? If I'm in cursor
and I um have an MCP server running and
that MCP server does something like
aentically or like something that's a
bit more you required a bit more
intelligence like for example summarize
my Reddit threads like a very simple
example like summarize something um how
do you do this because you require an
LLM for doing this but you on the MCP
server side so you have two options you
either add uh you know your um uh you
know anthropic SDK Okay. And require an
anthropic API key so that you can do
this call. But now you're in a weird
situation because the person in cursor
might use Gemini or might use like an
openi model but suddenly they also need
an like a like an anthropic key. Um so
how do you actually abstract this away?
And that is what sampling is about.
Sampling means that the server can go
back to the client. So the the MCP
server can go ask cursor can you
actually give me uh llm completion for
this bit and uh the client goes back and
uses the current selected model and
gives you back the completion. Um and
this is sadly not very widely um uh
widely widely implemented just yet but I
think it will uh become a quite an
interesting foundational piece to to
agents and quite interesting to use also
in these type of IDE situations. Um and
so with that then you can do something
very fun um because now this whole thing
becomes recursive um by the fact that
you can take an MCP server or build an
MCP server that exposes some form of
like intelligent workflow something
that's cool you want to do but itself
might use tools from an MCP from other
MCP servers and so it implements an MCP
client. So you can build these little
programs that are both a client and a
server. they expose a server upwards to
the user in the LLM and they expose a
client so that they can use MCP servers
themselves and now you can chain them
indefinitely long
um for some definition of indefinite um
and um you then have the interesting
property that because the way sampling
works if they all well behaved MCP
citizens um the last server in the row
when it wants a completion
from the LLM provider, it will be passed
all the way upwards and the one that
controls the whole inference stack for
this for the the inference that's
happening is the user and the LLM. And
so you can build these like graphs of um
of like these agentic graphs um of MCP
client server combinations with some
sort of logic in in your favorite
agentic framework in between um that
still is completely model agnostic and
you can just flip the model right and
that is actually cool if you
want to do something like evolves for
example with this and you can evol
different models against this. So this
is a really fun little exercise that
people don't see because I don't think
not necessarily everybody has recognized
this like recursive pattern that we have
deliberately built into the
protocol. Um and of course this kind of
comp composability and sampling then can
be used for these like wider
orchestration agents and you can totally
see you know an orchestr like an like an
orchestrator agent using like something
like pedantic AI and then it like farms
out to like your analysis agent or your
coding agent your research agent some of
them might be because they're we we use
Rewind MCP some of them might be not
even on your local machine anymore and
they might be somewhere else in your
data center they might be completely
different providers um you know be it
the PayPals the cloud flares whatever it
might be and so I think that's a really
fun pattern that you that you get from
this like sampling bit um that I wish
more people would do and more people
would experiment with and that I feel in
this year that is so much about agents
and people talk about agents uh I think
will be very very interesting for people
uh to explore
um yeah so this is fun uh this was like
some random bit that I that that very
few people have heard about so I I
thought is interesting no matter how
useful it is to you. Um what's next for
MCP?
Um at the moment there's a few bits I
think that are interesting the MCP land.
Um the first uh one is of course um
dealing with um the the popularity we're
we we have gained. Um we're adding more
SDKs as we speak. Um I'm I'm super happy
to um have the uh the Microsoft folks
and I think one or two of them are here
today have contributed the C car C uh
SDK and doing a tremendous job um in in
maintaining that. Um the the Spring
folks still did a great job in
maintaining the Java SDK. Uh we have
Google probably doing a Go SDK. Um, so
there's a bunch of action in that in the
in the like SDK world that I'm very very
happy. Uh, the pedantic folks have done
a great job uh being much better at
Python than I am for the Python SDK. So
I appreciate that a lot. Um, and so
there's a lot of that that is like
normal ongoing um, uh, like maintenance
of the of the project. Um, but then
there there are two really big pieces
that have come together just about now.
Um the one is this uh stateless HTTP
with optional SSE bit which is was a
very valid criticism of the original
protocol to make it really hard to to
scale it up. So for this like remote SAS
world is kind of hard to do. Uh and so
we have added optional
um uh HTTP with SSE. Um so you know the
server can be basically pure HTTP but if
it really wants to it can also open a
stream um and that will really enable
people to like scale these things
significantly better. And the second big
piece is the authorization part um that
we just added. So what you will be able
to you can just a you will authorize
with either a central entity in your
enterprise or with whatever account you
have. So you will go and you know
authorize with um I don't know superbase
and then you just have access to your
superbase accounts via your LLM and all
you did is you put in one URL into like
cursor and I think that would be really
really really cool. Um there's some bits
and pieces uh about enterprise
authorization that we're figuring out
and I'm uh exceptionally happy that
actually the oath spec people themselves
are jumping in and helping me out to
figure out to how to become an
enterprise uh expert uh in a week. uh
not recommended. Um the second part to
that is we are starting to build towards
an official registry. I'm sure everyone
of you who might have used MCP has run
into this interesting problem of like
how do I find good MCP servers? Uh how
do I discern what is good, what is bad,
how do you even know where to find them
in the first place? Um and that's a
interesting problem for now but it
becomes a really interesting problem
when people want to um either
automatically install these type of
things or have them have like a surface
that is like not the internet like
imagine like VS Code like how you
install it directly from VS Code and
these type of things. Um and so we're
just going to build a central registry.
Um like helps with
discoverability centralization bits and
and verification bits. Um it's in the
works. It turns out building registries
is not trivial. Uh also not recommended.
Um but what it really does is once you
have this you can on one side like have
things like you know Z VS code all these
sub editors like look at the same
central registry find the same things
that might have some form of trust um
and then install them from there. That's
really cool. But you also can like
imagine a world where um with additional
trust mechanisms and certifications and
so on agents might install some of them
themselves.
Um and so discoverability will be a will
be a big part here. Um other pieces
we're thinking about um the protocol is
fairly fairly bound to text somewhat at
the moment and there are definitely
different modalities that models have
and so we're thinking a lot about that.
With that obviously comes streaming. Uh
streaming in general is already a thing
that we kind of want because uh large
tool calls obviously at the moment are
like not streamed and that's kind of
annoying to people because they kind of
want to display these type of things. Um
so we want to do more of that. Um we
want to do more of like what we call
namespacing which is just basically
people going to build MCP proxies. Uh
and there's a sense of like how do I
maintain the original like hierarchy uh
from the original servers and for that I
need namespacing so that you don't have
the same
five right file tools uh in the same
namespace basically. Um and then there's
something that's dear to my heart. I
feel at the moment LLMs are a little bit
I I feel sometimes LLMs are a bit like
my my weird little neighbor um that um
that is really really smart has read the
whole internet uh but only talks to me
when I go knock at the door uh open some
like open the door uh and then you know
I get to ask a question uh and then when
they have uh when I have mentioned it
they give me a really good answer and
then they close the door uh and I shall
never receive anything practice. ly from
them, right? I wish they would come over
just once and tell me about the cool
news they have seen yesterday. And so
what I would want to have more is
something that is a bit more uh allowing
us to be proactive um so that I can get
up in the morning like I'm I'm an I'm a
um a recovering Eve Online player. Um,
and so, uh, I would love to just get up
in the morning and get news, uh, uh,
from, uh, my own MCP server using an LLM
about like, um, in in the application I
trust the most, um, about about, uh, Eve
Online. Um, uh, yeah. So, I would love
to do that and I'm sure nobody's going
to build that for me. So, cool. So,
that's a bit of that, uh, a bit of an
overview of MCP. Uh thanks for listening
and yeah we might have uh a bit of time
for for some
question. Thank you very much David for
that excellent talk. Lots of food for
thought there I'm sure we've got time
for two questions but then after that
we've we've still got the space for
another half an hour so you'll have more
chances to to chat to folks here. So
questions.
Yes. Go ahead. Um hi there. Uh thank you
for your nice talk and um so I I I think
there's a lot of discussions recently
online about the safety for MCP
protocol. So um I was wondering besides
the specification the registry uh what
are you guys working on to like uh
improve the security?
That's a very good question. Um
so there's a few aspects to that. So
we're currently mostly in the uh
situation where we gather feedback for
the most part and and look into what are
the next steps to take. I think I I
really want
to I don't want to figure this out by
myself. I think there are people
security experts in the world that are
better suited than myself to do this.
And so I'd love to like get just like a
figure out how we get a proactive like
collaboration and um with the security
community going to figure out what
pieces are um are are needed to
um to secure the bits a little bit more.
Um there's another aspect of that that I
want to be a bit more clear and I'm not
sure how these things fit in. I feel
some of the concerns at the moment for
example are general concerns that apply
to any type of problem and any type of
protocol basically. So for example con
like um an example is like people that
uh are very worried about like um your
MCP local MCP server being able to um to
have malicious intent then that's a very
classic example of like if you download
uh executable to your computer and
starting it then maybe you are a bit
responsible to figuring out if it it
does not delete your files. Um but but
there is more to that and I think there
are bits to like um making sure that at
least for example tools haven't changed
in between calls and these type of
things that you that that can be done in
the protocol and there are bits that
that are purely lying outside of the
protocol and outside of like a more like
supply chain attack kind of kind of
problem and I'm sure there will be
plenty of companies that will try to
figure that one out. Let's do one more
USA.
So one question I had particularly links
to security but is observability. So
when you mentioned that you can chain
many MCP servers together. So they will
fail at one point. Yeah. So how do you
actually push that? So to the point that
you had the panty so the log fire
earlier. So if you have several inch
chain and one fails so how that logs and
how that observability is propagated
across the the chains. Um that's a good
question. How does observability work?
Um the reality is at the moment um the
protocol has no offerings around
observability and it's something that
interesting enough Samuel has brought up
very very early. Um and I think
uh he's right in that sense that the
protocol should probably have a way that
is similar to sampling of like basically
have
have like like pushes upwards to the
client and the client can decide what to
do with it. Let's say you have logs
already. So it's in theory the server
can present logs to the we have we have
logs. Yeah. Yeah. Logs. But it's like
it's not telemetry, right? Like we have
logs at the moment. So you can already
Thank you Samuel for for for helping me
here. Uh we have logs already. So you
can already push logs upwards to the
client. Um but I think for observability
more like open telemetry, I think that
we're open to like seeing an RFC in the
in the world. Um it's something that is
given like authorization and streaming
and other bits a bit lower on my
personal list. So I will not I will
probably not work on it myself but this
is an open protocol and I really really
really just want to encourage people to
sit down write the RFC uh and do look at
addition I think and we're very open to
these and some you know some of like
some of the additions to the protocol
like like audio modality for example we
did not add some other people like
suggested it and Microsoft currently has
a really good RFC towards enterprise
authorization um changes in in in the
making and to again um I think something
that's worth considering but something I
I personally will not work on.
All right, I think we're going to leave
it there. Please join me in thanking all
our speakers from this evening. Jason,
thank you. Anuk, thank you. Samuel,
thank you. And David, thank you very
much.